We introduce generative
experience, a paradigm where the
interaction through which a
mental health intervention is
enacted is not fixed in advance,
but constructed at runtime from
the user's context and
intervention demand. We
instantiate this paradigm in
GUIDE, a system for generative
UI for interactive digital
experiences. Our system, GUIDE,
has three components. First,
context elicitation. GUIDE begins
with a short, structured
conversation to understand the
user's situation, not just what
they're stressed about, but how
they describe it, what feels
within their control, what their
circumstances are right now.
This gets distilled into a
summary that drives everything
downstream. Second, intervention
selection. Given that context,
GUIDE generates multiple
candidate interventions drawn
from a broad space of CBT
informed strategies like
cognitive restructuring,
behavioral activation, regulation
techniques. Candidates are
evaluated by an LLM judge
against rubrics developed with
clinical experts capturing
things like safe sequencing,
feasibility, and specificity to
the user's situation. The
highest scoring intervention is
selected. Third, and this is the
new part, UX selection. Given
the selected intervention in the
user's context, GUIDE generates
the interaction experience
itself. It composes sequences of
modular elements, audio
messages, timers, text inputs,
visual components. The same
intervention can be enacted
through different structures
depending on what the context
calls for. A second set of
rubrics evaluates candidate
experiences for usability
alignment with the intervention
and specificity to the user. The
result is a combinatorial design
space, not a fixed interface.
Every user gets a different form
of UX structure. These three
stages mean that both what
support is offered and how it is
experienced are generated at
runtime, tailored to each
person's context and not fixed
in advance. Let's see GUIDE in
action. Imagine a user is
stressed about a job interview
tomorrow. They start by sharing
their situation by typing or by
voice. GUIDE asks a few short,
structured questions - what's
hardest about it? What feels
within their control, what their
circumstances are right now?
Once the conversation is
complete, the system distills it
into a summary the user can read
and edit before anything else
happens. Based on this context,
GUIDE selects an intervention
and constructs a user experience
that can guide the user through
a stress reduction activity.
Parts of it can contain an
encouraging audio message
personalized to what the user
shared, followed by a prompt to
verbalize their thoughts and
plans out loud or in writing.
The audio reflects their
specific situation. The follow
up prompt asks them to
articulate what they'll do next.
But this is just one of many
possible experiences GUIDE might
construct. The system could
instead generate a timer-based
activity asking the user to
spend 60 seconds on a focused
task before reflecting. Or a
short video walking them through
a mindfulness or grounding
exercise. Or a visual card pair
two contrasting frames helping
the user picture the shift from
where they are now to where they
could be. Or a guided Breathing
exercise to regulate before they
engage with the harder
reflection work. Or a simple
text based rehearsal activity.
Any of these experiences, any
combination, any sequence, and
crucially, the content of each
one reflects what this specific
person shared about their
situation. The questions use
their words. The audio speaks to
their context. The prompts point
to their next concrete step.
None of it is templated, the
intervention, the modality, the
structure, all of it is
constructed at runtime for this
person, in this moment. We
evaluated GUIDE in a preregistered between participant
experiment with 237
participants, comparing it
against a strong LLM based
cognitive restructuring system.
GUIDE produced significantly
greater stress reduction and
better user experience. Beyond
outcomes, GUIDE generated a
genuine diversity of
experiences, combining different
CBT techniques and multimodal
interaction types across
participants. No two sessions
were the same. In short, GUIDE
is a first step toward systems
that adapt not just what support
is offered, but how it is
experienced. Our results suggest
this capacity can improve mental
health outcomes, and we believe
generative experience opens a
promising direction for the
field. Thank you for watching
this video.